Mariano Riva Palacio Collection:
University of Texas at Austin
- Enero-Junio 1850
  - 3916 Silva, Ignacio. Cuernavaca, March 6, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    $1,000 borrowed by the Ayuntamiento from the Ayuntamiento de Tepalcingo for contract with Lucas Alamán; plan to rebuild the prison and Palace; construction of roads and aqueducts.
  - 3917 Tapia, Ildefonso. Mexico, March 6, 1850. ALS., 4 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Settlement of dispute between Mixquiahuala and the Cortina family; storage of grain in Mixquiahuala; suggested solution. Includes another copy, signed. Includes note:
    - a. Mariano Arista: [Nota a Riva Palacio.] Palacio Nacional de México, March 11, 1850. Copy. 1 l. f. 2. Recommendation for settlement without loss of crops on cultivated land.
  - 3918 Pérez Palacios, Ángel. Cuernavaca, March 6, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Loan by the Ayuntamiento de Tepalcingo to pay for education of local boy; Cuernavaca's need for money to rebuild the palacio as government offices; cooperation with General Álvarez on road Mexico-Acapulco.
  - 3919 Barrientos, José María. Mexico, March 6, 1850. LS. 2 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Exaggeration of charges against Padre Mendoza of Apan; his Indian ancestry; Quintana; Germán.
  - 3920 Azcoytia, Fernando. Puebla, March 7, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for back pay; description of his poverty.
  - 3921 Terreros, M. Mexico, March 7, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Delivery of letters to Quijano, Pérez Palacios, Noriega, and Sein; movement of bandit group from Jalpa to Tula District; Subprefecto de Jilotepec; interference with collection of capitation tax; military aid recommended for Tula; Juzgado de Pachuca; Escudero.
  - 3922 Piedra, Mariano de la. [Carta a Epigmenio de la Piedra.] Coatepec, March 7, 1850. ALS., 3 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for intervention with the governor to maintain the town's separation from Zacualpam; article in the Porvenir; second reading of bill in Legislature. Includes fragment of letter from A[gustín] D[íaz], Mexico, January 16, 1850 on disagreement between Governor of Puebla and the Ayuntamiento over Church affairs.
  - 3923 Andrade, Cristóbal. [Carta a Mariano Arista.] Huejutla, March 7, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Recommendation for Lic. Hierro, Juez interino of the Partido de Yahualica for position with the Juzgado de Yahualica.
  - 3924 Villar, José del. Coyoacán, March 7, 1850. LS., 1 l. 22 × 27 cm.
    Efforts to have a tax placed on gambling during the Easter period as a revenue measure; support of Zerecero.
  - 3925 Sein, A. Tula, March 8, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Settlement of local rebellion; orders to the Subprefecto de Ixmiquilpan; continued danger from Indians; linguistic ability of Subprefecto of Ixmiquilpan in Otomí and mejicano; removal of Subprefecto de Actopan; trouble between Mixquiahuala and Hacienda de Cortina.
  - 3926 Barrera y Prieto, Francisco. Mexico, March 8, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Claim for debts owed by the government; claim for repayment of damages suffered during the U.S. occupation in the Fábrica de Pansacola, the Plaza de toros, and the Finca de Tlalpam, recoverable under Law of June 14, 1848; contract awarded Laforgue and Rubio; aid of Zerecero; poverty of General Barrera.
  - 3927 Oliveros, Ignacio. Morelos, March 8, 1850. LS., 3 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Bandit plans for attack on Feria de Tepalcingo; alert at Matamoros; Alcalde Juan Rodríguez of Morelos; plot in house of Tijera; report in the Palanca; report of illness. Includes also unsigned note referring to events of July, `28[?]; travel with Matías Baños of Tulancingo and Manuel Sánchez of Cuautla to Morelos, Nava, and Totolapa; robbery at Totola; Andrés Montes de Oca; Luis Bastida; Comandante de Seguridad de Méjico Miguel González; trip from Texcoco to Chimalquacan (Chimalhuacán?); Captain Araus (?); meeting with Pérez at Ayotla; search at Río Frío; aid to Pérez at Texmeluca[n]; Prefecto de Texcoco.
  - 3928 Aguilar, Luis María. Mexico, March 9, 1850. ALS., 5 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Notes on controversy between Acuatula and Zoquiapa; Prefecto de Chalco; Supporting letters are attached.
    - a. (No. 2). L. M. A., [Carta a Mauricio Bassoco] Mexico, January 19, 1850. Copy. 1 l. f. 2. Opposition to new measurement of land.
    - b. (No. 4). Unsigned copy. [Carta a Mauricio Bassoco.] Mexico, March 2, 1850. 1 l. f. 3. Opposition to boundary changes at Ixtapaluca.
    - c. [Carta a Mariano Barroso, demás autoridades y vecinos de Acuautla.] Mexico, March 1, 1850. Unsigned copy. 1 l. f. 4. Opposition to interference with Hacienda de Zocuapa (Zoquiapa?).
  - 3929 Márquez, Antonio. Jonacatepec, March 9, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for excuse from Guardia Nacional for two Indians.
  - 3930 Chávez, J. Lorenzo. Metztitlán, March 9, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Collection of the new tax.
  - 3931 [Díaz,] Ag[ustí] n. Tlalnep[]a (?), March 9, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Agreement with the Prefecto de Cuautitlán over use of the Guardia Nacional; Terreros; tax collection; Zumpango; San Ángel; Tlalpam; cholera cases in Huisquiluca. Riva Palacio addressed as primo.
  - 3932 Arista, Mariano. Mexico, March 9, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Approval of request for protection of property involved in a suit by Quintana Roo.
  - 3933 Goribar, J. de. Casasano, March 10, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Preparation of padrones as basis for taxation.
  - 3934 Pérez Palacios, Ángel. Cuernavaca, March 10, 1850. LS., 5 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Report on meeting of creditors of the Hacienda del Estado; discussion of the Law of October 16, 1849; partial arrangements for payments. Includes unsigned, undated draft of a memorandum for the creditors; Aparicio Zedillo; P. Palacios; Ramo de aguardiente y de azúcar. Includes also “Relacion de los individuos á quienes se contrae mi carta de 10 del corriente con las anotaciones que me han parecido conbeniente,” same date. 2 leaves. Lists Ignacio Silva, Florentino Ramos, Pedro Valdovinos, José Simón Cagide, Julián Figueroa, Herenlano (?) Juárez, Francisco Figueroa; José Salazar; Rafael Sámano. Mateo Salazar, Rafael Durán, Luis Marzán, Doña María Pérez Palacios, Antonio Bobadilla, José María Patiño, Ignacio Silva of the Hacienda de Dolores, Gerónimo Guerrero, Francisco Pérez Palacios, Francisco Bustillos, Miguel Escobar, Ignacio Sánchez, Lorenzo Calderón, Antonio Gutiérrez, José Diego Bermúdez, Concha y Ortiz, and Ventura Orellana; claims from U. S. occupation.
  - 3935 Alamán, Lucas. Cuernavaca, March 10, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Residence at Atlacomulco for improvement of lung ailment; danger of attacks at Sultepec; purchase of land. Includes draft of reply.
  - 3936 Arista, Mariano. Mexico, March 11, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Request that lands in litigation near Mixquiahuala be planted regardless of the litigation; Sra. Cortina; suffering caused previous year.
  - 3937 Cumplido, Ignacio. Mexico, March 11, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Transmittal of copies of El Siglo with article on the policy in Mexico State; rebellion of Cardonal; account with Maneyro; Barajas.
  - 3938 Haro y Tamariz, Antonio de. Mexico, March 11, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Partial payment of loan to Sánchez Solís; loan for the Instituto Literario; recommendation for Tomás Prieto; support of Arista and Trigueros; Zedillo.
  - 3939 Morquecho, Mariano. Zacualtipán, March 11, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Co-operation promised in collection of tax; failure of predecessor Juan Ugalde to turn over local archives; need to start all files anew; illness; Juez de Hacienda; gift of bobo.
  - 3940 Arista, Mariano. Mexico, March 12, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Dispatch of troops under Colonel Echagaray.
  - 3941 DIRECCIÓN GENERAL DE ADUANAS MARÍTIMAS FRONTERIZAS, Y RENTAS NO ESTANCADAS. Mexico, March 12, 1850. ALS. Signed: Ignacio Sierra y Rosso. 2 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Settlement of case of widow of Moya; intrigues of Antonio Herrera, Administrador de Chalco; opposition of Caudás; condemnation in El Siglo and Monitor withdrawn. Includes draft of answer, March 14.
  - 3942 Zamora, Blas. Texcoco, March 12, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Mission of Rebollar to Chalco and Tehuacán for help; reports that the Sargento de Seguridad Pública will gather forces from Río Frío and announce for Santa Anna.
  - 3943 Lacunza, [José María]. Mexico, March 12, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Offer of aid in protection of Texcoco; reported release of prisoners.
  - 3944 Álvarez, Diego. Acapulco, March 12, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Opposition to Luciano Cantú; loss of father's support; complaint made by Salazar in the Puebla Legislature; Comisión de puntos constitucionales of Michoacán; controversy over division of Coyuca; removal to Iguala; dissension within the state legislature; defeat of Aburto.
  - 3945 Maruri, Francisco. [Carta a Esteban Vicente León.] Mineral de Santo Tomás, March 12, 1850. ALS., 3 l. 15 × 21 cm.
    Departure of Prefecto for Otzoloapan, Tejupilco; abuses by Antonio Cornejo; Pedro Nava; Marcial Ávila; the community terrorized; assault by Onofre Arroyo on Avelino Valle, Polonio Concha, José Luisa, and Teodoro Rosales; murder of José María González, alias el Espíritu; refusal of Cornejo to surrender arms; arms furnished Banegas; arms taken from Andrés Alvarado; Pedro Bárcenas.
  - 3946 Sein, A. Tula, March 12, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Fuerza Rural and Guardia Nacional troops offered to help in quelling Cardonal rebellion; Ixquiquilpan (Ixmiquilpan?); collection of the tax; danger of Indian uprising in Acambay in imitation of Yucatán; Ildefonso Tapia; Tepeji. Letter sent via Zamora.
  - 3947 Zamora, Blas. Texcoco, March 13, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Report on abortive pro-Santa Anna revolt; release of Pedro Beltrán from jail; surrender to Rebollar; support expected from Juchi and Mexico; arrest of the sergeant by Herrera; escape of Zenón Sánchez toward Córdoba and Xocoatlaco (?); help requested from Chalco and Teotihuacán; message to Arista; Sargento Guerrero; Pedro Salazar; Tonchi.
  - 3948 Terreros, Manuel. Mexico, March 13, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Pay requested for Manuel Veytia for service as Juez interino de Zumpango; end of Cardonal affair; Aguirre.
  - 3949 Garrido, J. M. Atoyac, March 13, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 26 cm.
    Travel of Francisco Velázquez to Mexico; Juan Francisco López; complaint of mistreatment of lower classes; need for government reform; escape of prisoners at Tepetlastoque; Tepetlaoxtoc (?).
  - 3950 [Díaz,] Ag[ustí] n. Zumpango, March 13, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Visit to the district to encourage payment of tax; Cuautitlán; Pedro Rodríguez; trip to Tepotzotlán and Tlalpam; complaint filed by Juez de Letras Lic. Leocadio López; Lic. Veytia; anecdote concerning Gómez el Patriota.
  - 3951 Téllez, Joaquín. Cuernavaca, March 13, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for continued possession of the section of artillery.
  - 3952 Cueva, Ramón de la. [Carta a Luis Alcocer.] March 13, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 16 × 21 cm.
    Dissension between the Hacienda de Tlapisalco and towns of Zumpahuacán and San Pablo; Dolores Bernal requested to allow interview; meeting in Toluca; Tenancingo.
  - 3953 Gómez Pedraza, Manuel. Mexico, March 13, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Prohibition of gambling at San Agustín de las Cuevas during Easter; effort of Ayuntamiento de Tlalpan to appeal the ruling to the Legislature.
  - 3954 Barrio, Juan M. del. Temixco, March 14, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Complaint against Señora Pavón; Pancho Camposo; Lacunza; Cuesta de Huichilao (?); Barrevechea.
  - 3955 Terreros, Manuel. Mexico, March 14, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Texcoco incident reported to González of the Police; Zamora; Oliveros.
  - 3956 Atristain, Miguel. Mexico, March 14, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Interview with Bernardo Copca; proposals by Tapia; legal study of rights of the towns as opposed to those of the haciendas.
  - 3957 Barrera, Ignacio de la. Mexico, March 14, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Transmittal of son's resignation; request for pay to be delivered in Washington.
  - 3958 Escudero, Agustín. Texcoco, March 14, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for position as Juez de primera instancia; recommendation by Pedraza, Otero, Lafragua, and Gamboa; vacancies in Pachuca and Tlalnepantla; warning against Beltrán; Arista; Rebollar.
  - 3959 Cevallos, Juan B. Morelia, March 15, 1850. LS. 2 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead of Governor of Michoacán.
    Cholera epidemic in Puruándiro; reports by Malo; comparison with 1833; remedy recommended by the Academia de Medicina; preventive measures; Junta de caridad; transmittal of copies of decrees.
  - 3960 Díez de Sollano, José María. Mexico, March 15, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 26 cm.
    Notice of opening of new course in Agriculture at the College, supported by Río de la Loza, Benigno Bustamante, Joaquín Velázquez de León, and Fonseca; aid of Bustillos; Vicente's recommendation that Carlos take the course.
  - 3961 García, Eusebio. Mexico, May 15, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Invitation to meet with representatives of towns near his hacienda del Mayorazgo declined, for himself and son Tomás; refusal of towns' requests.
  - 3962 Rossel, Juan. Texcoco, March 15, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Controversy with Campos over payments to Guadalupe during his absence in Mexico.
  - 3963 Herrera y Campos, Francisco. Texcoco, March 15, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Services of Sargento Guerrero and Cabo Zenón Sánchez; difficulties with the Juez and with Beltrán.
  - 3964 Riva Palacio, Vicente. San Gregorio, March 15, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Recommendation that Carlos take the agriculture curriculum; study of French, English, drawing, mathematics, physics, and chemistry included.
  - 3965 Arista, Mariano. March 16, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Efforts to settle the problem with Calderón and in Texcoco.
  - 3966 Ruiz, Juan. [Carta a Ignacio Oliveros.] Chalco, March 16, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Imprisonment of soldiers Sixto Moreno, Mariano Gómez, and Francisco Huellotenco; release on recommendation of Cura de Ameca; travel to Ameca and Puebla; Valeriano Pérez; case against José Patricio; pressure brought on Juez de Letras; Sabino Flores.
  - 3967 Alvarado de Lara, José María. [Carta a Anselmo Zurutuza.] Venta de Córdoba, March 16, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Pursuit of bandits refused by authorities; robbery of stagecoach; criminal acts by Zenón Sánchez and Sargento Guerrero in Tepetlastoque and Texcoco; support of Santa Anna, Hacienda de Xocuatlaco (?); Agustín Manzo; Ignacio Cid; Miguel Gutiérrez; Sargento Remijo Bernal; Pedro Beltrán de los Ríos; Juan Ruiz; robbery of Otero; Licenciado Sierra, Juez de Letras de Chalco; Oliveros.
  - 3968 Cruz, Agustín. Tenango, March 16, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Escape of José López; arrival of Oliveros; Tinam[]o; Partido de Tenancingo (?); Tunaloya; Indian uprising in Ocuila, Tepexoxuca, and Joquicingo.
  - 3969 _____. Tenería, March 16, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Readiness to furnish military aid; delay in preparing padrones; Arnaldo and Fernando Rundo (?); cholera.
  - 3970 Sáenz de Sicilia, José I. Apam, March 16, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Meeting of hacendados to discuss collection of tax; payments to laborers at Easter at Apam, Almoloya, and Tepeapulco.
  - 3971 Zurutuza, A[nselmo]. Mexico, March 16, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Work on Cuernavaca road; dependence on cuadrillas; report from Venta de Córdoba.
  - 3972 Álvarez, Juan. Iguala, March 16, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Directions for Administradores de Acapulco, Chilapa, and Taxco; pay for Juan Velázquez de León; debts of the new state; publication of the Ley orgánica; movement of government to Tixtla.
  - 3973 León Acosta, Benito. Chalco, March 16, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Surrender of wharf at Chalco to Vicente Gómez; canoe traffic; roadbuilding.
  - 3974 Martínez, Primitivo. Chalco, March 16, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Progress of public works; repair to the city wall, the cemetery, and chapels; the Mexico-City road; planting of trees along the road; expenses of José Castro and Cristóbal Cano (?) for repairs to the Casas consistoriales; repair to the Panótica or Penitenciaría; need for engineer; Philadelphia prison; Zavala; Otero; Francisco [Martínez?].
  - 3975 Calderón, Lorenzo. Tem[]c, March 16, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Return from Otzoloapan; report of Prefecto Cruz on the Hacienda de Tenayac; meeting of citizens of este mineral and la Villa del Valle; Otzoloapan to belong to Toluca and Ixtapan del Oro to go with Sultepec; Guardia nacional of Otzoloapan and Santo Tomás released; order of Arizcorreta withdrawn; difficulty with Cornejo; Esteban V. León; hostility of San Lucas and Acatitlán; Tejupilco.
  - 3976 Navarro, Jesús. Hacienda de Apizaco, March 16, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Success in lawsuit; peacefulness in Yautepec.
  - 3977 Calderón, Lorenzo. Tem[]c, March 16, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Rumors of pro-Santa Anna agitation in Tenayac by folowers of Zamudio; Tejup[il]co; leadership of Captain Santos Barroeta in Amatepec Tlatlaya; rumors denied by Esteban López, owner of Hacienda de Ixtapan, and by Joaquín de la Cueva, owner of Haciendas of Lubianos and Bejucos; failure of plan in Sultepec; Cabecillas Sordo Campuz[an]o, Luis Martínez; influence of Padre Alcocer in Tenancingo; attempt against Olaguíbel and Zamudio; Zumpahuacán; Mineral de Guadalupe; reinforcements needed in Zacualpam; movement to establish separate state of Toluca; report by Eligio García on uprising quelled by Eduardo Rodríguez, the Alcalde in Sultepec.
  - 3978 Silva, Ignacio. Cuernavaca, March 17, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Money to be sent from Tepalcingo; support of plan of Lucas Alamán; Ángel Pérez Palacios; resignation of Villaseñor as Prefecto de Cuernavaca; Londres.
  - 3979 García, José María. Valle, March 17, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Imprisonment of Joaquín Rebollar in Otzoloapan over fiscal irregularities in Temascaltepec; intervention requested.
  - 3980 Cruz, Agustín. Tenería, March 18, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Collection of tax; request for reinforcements.
  - 3981 Calderón, Lorenzo. Tem[]c, March 18, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Danger of rebellion in Sultepec; Alcalde de Amatepec; Archundia; danger from Zamudio in Tenancingo or Zumpahuacán.
  - 3982 Campos, José Mariano. Administración principal de la Renta del Tabaco del Distrito y Estado de México. Mexico, March 18, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Establishment of tobacco shops in Tlaxcala; opposition of the Governor of Puebla.
  - 3983 Herrera y Campos, Francisco. Texcoco, March 18, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Surrender of Cabo Zenón Sánchez; reinforcements received from Córdoba, Teotihuacán, and Ozumba; help by Oliveros; pursuit of Beltrán; Rebollar; Noriega.
  - 3984 Riva Palacio, Mariano. [Borrador de carta a Vicente.] Toluca, March 18, 1850. ALS. 1 l. 21 × 26 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Transmittal of letters for the Rector; recommendations for Carlos.
  - 3985 Sánchez Munibe, Joaquín. Yautepec, Fielato de Yautepec, March 18, 1850. 2 l. 21 × 27 cm., 1 l. 16 × 22 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Bond posted by Esteban Goyeneche; difficulties with the Juez de Letras in reconciling accounts. Includes draft of answer supporting the Juez de Letras.
  - 3986 Icaza, Antonio de. Mexico, March 19, 1850. LS., 4 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Support of San Gregorio; efforts of Ayuntamiento de San Juan Teotihuacán to prevent water from reaching Haciendas of San José Acolman; precedent set in 1824; demands of the Indians; appeal to the Juez de Letras and the Prefecto de Texcoco; duties as Administrador de los bienes del colegio. Includes documents: Letter of Icaza to Prefecto Francisco Herrera.
    - a. Icaza: [Copia de carta al Prefecto Francisco Herrera en Texcoco.] Mexico, December 14, 1849. 1 l. f. 2. Statement of difficulties over boundaries of land owned by San Gregorio.
    - b. Icaza: [Informe.] December 14, 1849. 1 l. f. 2v. Statement of legal aspects of disagreement.
  - 3987 Arévalo Horcasitas, Luis. Tlayacapan, March 19, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Low teacher's salary blamed on poverty of the towns of Tlayacapan and Atlatla[h]uca; appeal for more funds.
  - 3988 Piedra, Epigmenio de la. Tenancingo, March 19, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Cousin Vicente Linares to be in the Legislature; use of marble stone; letter of brother Mariano, Alcalde de Coatepec on separation of Zacualpam.
  - 3989 Alcocer, Luis A. Lerma, March 19, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Opposition to intervention of Cueva in a legal suit.
  - 3990 Navarro, Esteban. Jilotepec, March 19, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 26 cm.
    Request for permanent appointment; refusal of José María Mateos to accept position.
  - 3991 Peña, J. de la. Morelos, March 19, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Exemption from tax requested for tower clock ordered from the United States; decision of the Vicario capitular on use of the cemetery.
  - 3992 Terreros, Manuel. Mexico, March 20, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 26 cm.
    Complaint of José Adalid against paying amortization tax; Convento de Santa Clara; Escribano Cueva.
  - 3993 Santín, Miguel. [Carta a Lorenzo Calderón.] Tejupilco, March 20, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Release of Juan Benítez; Joaquín Oribe's resignation; Esteban López; Tierra Caliente.
  - 3994 Gómez, José F. Tenam[]o, March 20, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Letter to Álvarez; Iguala; transfer of offices to Ciudad Guerrero protested.
  - 3995 Álvarez, Juan. Iguala, March 20, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request that Miguel Salgado be allowed to search the state archives for land titles in litigation.
  - 3996 Velázquez, J. Francisco. Moral, March 22, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Rumor of bandits hiding under protection of the Cura de Ameca after robbery of Puebla stagecoach.
  - 3997 Calderón, Lorenzo. Sultepec, March 22, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Investigation of rumors of rebellion about Temascaltepec; influence of the Texcoco incident; Sordo Campuzano; Santín, Alcalde de Tejupilco; Arista; Juez de Letras de Temascaltepec; Alcalde de Otzoloapam Rebollar; meeting suggested between Prefecto Cruz, representatives from El Valle, Tenayac, and Temascaltepec; Zacualpam; efforts in Ixtapan and Coatepec to be annexed to the Partido de Tenancingo; efforts of Tejupilco to become a partido; danger to Distrito de Sultepec.
  - 3998 Calderón, Lorenzo. [Carta a Mariano Arista.] Sultepec, March 22, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Inspection of Morelia boundaries; movement to join the Distrito de Toluca identified as political movement to arouse the Indians; surveillance over Cornejo; the Texcoco incident; leader identified as Padre Alcocer, who attacked Olaguíbel in Tenancingo; León; Zamudio; Zumpahuacán; other leaders: Campusano alias el Sordo, Captain Luis Martínez alias Chiquito, Captain Patricio Irias, Captain Basilio Antonio, Captain Ildefonso Casimiro; release of Zamudio when tried for treason in San Andrés de las Gamas; support of Riva Palacio and León; accusation against Arista by Diputado Herrera Zavala reported in El Monitor, No. 1758; Cuchiquillo.
  - 3999 Álvarez, Juan. [Carta al Lic. Trinidad Gómez.] Iguala, March 23, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Plans to move offices to Tixtla; Tenancingo; recommendation to Riva Palacio.
  - 4000 ESTADO DE GUERRERO. Iguala de Iturbide, Secretaría de la H. Legislatura Constituyente del Estado Libre y Soberano de Guerrero, March 23, 1850. Signed: E. Vargas and Juan Jose Calleja, diputados secretarios., 3 l. 21 × 31 cm.
    Transmittal of copy of the Decree making honorary citizens of certain individuals.